Praveen Menon

11109 Cavalier Court, Fairfax, VA – 220304 🏚

917-714-7314

http://www.pmenon.info

https://github.com/praveenmenon

Current Graduate student at George Mason University, Computer science Class of 2020. Experienced professional software developer who has worked with leaders in agile software development. Developed Mobile Apps in the Android and Amazon App Stores. Presented Home Automation projects at International GopherCon, Dubai and have emphasized the use of GoLang for Gaming. Equipped with problem solving skills, logical and structured thinking, attention to detail, and a sound knowledge of various programming languages, tools and different operating system to research and implement new ideas with an ability to work independently and in a team.

Education

Masters - Computer Science / George Mason University, Virginia
Bachelor of Engineering-Information Science / Vishvesvaraya Technological University

2018 - 2020

2010 - 2014

Technical Skills

Languages GoLang, Ruby on Rails, Java, Angular Js, Revel(GoLang), Bego (Golang), JavaScript, Node Js, Hapi JS

Database Postgres SQL, My SQL, Dynamo DB, Firebase.

Tools Postman - REST Client, AWS services (IOT, S3, Lambda, Dynamo DB, Alexa), Xcode, Github, JIRA, RSpec, Docker, Tomcat 8

Certifications Oracle Certified Web Component Developer using Java Technologies.

Experience

Research Assistant, Krasnow CNG / GMU, Virginia

2018 - present

- Developing and Maintaining neuromorpho.org which is a centrally curated inventory of digitally reconstructed neurons built in Java
- The website is built with JAVA and matlab, deployed using tomcat and used similarity searching algorithm to find similar neuron structures
- Used solar and similarity algorithm to simplify the searching and pagination of millions of neurons in neuromorpho.org

Software Developer / Qwinix Technologies, Mysore, India

2014 - 2018

- Developed skills for smart speaking devices like Amazon Echo and submitted 3 skills to app store.
- Developed APIs in Golang to create "Internet Of Things" using "Amazon Web Services" IOT services.
- Developed an online recruitment application with Golang API code and Angular JS as front-end to simplify the recruitment process
- Worked on AWS services for development, deployment and continues integration of web projects.

Qwinix Projects

- Vested Website developed to provide online platform for social investments built using Ruby on rails framework.
- rVidi A web and iOS application for recording, streaming, collaborating and sharing videos developed in Golang and Angular JS
- myAyu Home automation product built as an Alexa skill, web application in angular JS and mobile application in react native.
- Uvize Online teaching application with integrated functionalities for students built using angularJs and Ruby on Rails

Projects

- Maarga An Android application to report social issues to the concerned authorities using Golang
- Puzzle Boy A Node JS Alexa skill with machine learning to understand and improvise riddle puzzles
- Goodnight kiddo A Node JS project built in AWS Lambda, Dynamo DB and deployed using serverless architecture

Additional Skills

- Successfully completed training in Scrum Incremental Agile Software Development
- Developed training material for GoLang workshops that provided a standard for incoming trainees
- Conducted workshop for engineering students on Golang, Postgres SQL and REST API calls across the state of Karnataka, India
- Conducted the Code Yuddha 2016, Hackathon for software students across the state of Karnataka, India
- Organized "Mysore Alexa Skill Building" meetup